[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
hello everybody in today's podcast i
have the pleasure of introducing brian
oaken ryan is the author of the python
testing
with pi test or a book and this is the
subject of this which is by test and
python testing will be the topic of
today's podcast a little bit about brian
he is a passionate pythonista who loves
to talk about python and testing and he
is also a podcast host of his own he has
a podcast called testing code and he's
also the co-host of the python bytes
podcast which i personally listen to
it's a very good podcast you should
check out if you ever get a chance
welcome to the show ryan how are you
today
i'm great thanks for that nice
introduction great so just to get into
the first thing so just for everybody
what is pi test and why should i care
about pi test as a testing framework
well okay so first you kind of answered
the first part it is a testing framework
and hopefully you care about testing
your code now sometimes we have software
engineers that we have to convince that
they should test their code so let's
assume that you know that you should
well like maybe we shouldn't assume that
so i like to be proud of the code i
write and i like to be able to change it
i like to change like get the first pass
done and then be able to play with it
change it make it something i'm proud of
and a testing framework allows me the
freedom to do that because i know once i
have all the code working according to
my tests
then i can play with it i can change it
and refactor it and it'll still run so
that's that's one of the main reasons
why i like using a testing framework and
pi test in particular is really easy to
start because
it's just little test functions you can
just start right away with just writing
test underscore
something and it as a function and write
some code there that exercises your code
under test and that's it you've got to
test so you can get started really
easily
but then you can extend it and and have
basically the most complicated test
suite i can think of you can do in pi
test and so you can start easily and it
grows with you so awesome so as i
understand it then i test as a very
simple setup and it is convention based
so you do test underscore in front of
your file and it will automatically pick
up that file as a test file correct yeah
so the test underscores both the files
and the function names you can change
that you can have different things if
you like to have the
underscore test at the end of the file
or at the end of the function name you
can change that but most people don't
they just they're good with the
convention
right so python famously is a batteries
included kind of language right and we
know that there is a testing framework
built into python could you maybe
contrast by test and how how easy it is
versus the regular unit test
yeah so unit test is a actually an
incredible piece of software also so
unit test is the batteries included
version
and partly it's good to have a testing
framework within
the standard library so it can be used
to test python itself and the rest of
the standard library so but it's it's
very different than working with pi test
and if there's a notion of an x unit
style of test framework and unit test is
one of those
and what that style is is you
have a base class a base test class that
has and then with that it's a naming
convention as well you derive from that
base class and then you implement test
methods and then the test framework runs
those methods that you fill in now
because it's a base class you've got and
you're working within a class system
you've got a lot of that's where your
setup and teardown go is within the
class and then also with the assert
methods or part of that
pi test is a lot the one of the big
differences
is
that generally people don't use classes
with pi test you can you can even use
unit test as a base class if you want to
but you don't have to base it on
anything you can put them in classes but
it's more of a container to hold your
test code in there's actually a lot of
python developers that are using it
every day but they don't create their
own classes for anything else so one of
the reasons why i love to have people
especially in that situation use pi test
is because
that's a hurdle i've heard from a lot of
people of if i use unit tests i have to
go learn about object oriented
programming you don't really using unit
test doesn't require you to know very
much about object oriented programming
but that's kind of a barrier for some
people so with pi tests you don't have
to so that's one of the big differences
the other big noticeable difference is
that the assert method so pi test just
uses the built-in python assert method
and then
under the hood there are helper
functions that tear it apart and make it
so that you can see what failed if when
a failure happens you want to be able to
like let's say if i say assert a equals
b
if that's not true
i'd like to be able to see what a and b
were
and pi test gives you that whereas if
you try to use do that just that normal
bear assert within unit test
you'll just get you know false is not
true which isn't very helpful so unit
test got around that by doing a whole
bunch of assert methods extra ones like
us or equals assert not equals there's a
whole slew of them and then pi test kind
of avoids that by having some under the
hood stuff going on it actually rewrites
your source code for you while it's uh
so the getting into the weeds but when
python runs it creates bytecode and in
that bytecode process pi test can
intercept that
and turn asserts that are in your tests
or there's other ways to get other code
in there but mostly the asserts in your
test to take those assert calls and
interrupt the bytecode translation and
call these other helper functions that
allow it to make a better
assert output awesome
right right so i mean like you said it's
a little bit lower level and into the
beats but i think it kind of illustrates
the philosophy of fighters which is kind
of like to optimize for
developer happiness and development uses
right so it's kind of very focused on
making the usability of testing
very good for a developer yes and then
the readability of the test so when
you're reading a test you can and that's
a big thing around the pi test
philosophy
is to make tests very readable so we can
have just normal asserts they they just
look natural in your code and then
you're hopefully getting extra stuff out
of your test so the test is really
focused on really what part of the
system you're testing right now
so right
so usually even when you kind of try to
start testing any kind of non-trivial
system more than like a simple python
script but even sometimes simple python
scripts as well you need to do some sort
of testing setup and tear down there
might be a database connection to create
or even kind of mock something or
do something with an api
how does setup and tear down work with
my test so what are the concepts there
that's another good comparison with pi
test and x unit style frameworks because
the next unit style framework
traditionally will have like special
setup and tear down they're actually
called that setup and tear down or set
up class and teardown class and those
methods within and the difference really
between setup and setup class is whether
or not you call the framework calls
those functions before every test or
just before and after the class so if
i've got like say three methods within a
class
do i call it once for all three methods
or
so there's the x unit style is really
around like having these hooks that you
can put code in for before and after
your test is run the difficulty often
comes in with
like sometimes that's not enough levels
so like the database example that you
brought up that's a very common one i
want to connect to a database and the
connect setting and up connecting it
maybe filling it with a whole bunch of
dummy data so that i can run some tests
on it that's kind of a costly thing that
i don't really want to do for absolutely
every test so i can set that up once for
all of my tests
and then any other test that needs to
use that can grab that and maybe reset
it to a known state and that's cheaper
than creating the whole thing so i can
maybe roll back transactions or or
somehow reset it to a known state now
within this two level thing is possible
within
x unit frameworks but you have to take
advantage of like class and method level
setup and teardown but it's a little you
have to kind of do the paperwork
yourself whereas in pi test instead of
you can do that with implied tests but
the preferred way is to use fixtures and
fixtures are a named thing so you a test
that needs the database or it needs a
clean database can just
have a fixture named that like clean
database or something
now that
can be in different scopes the fixtures
can be in different scopes they can and
by that being we've got function
class module
package
and session so that you can have like a
fixture used by all of your test code
even if they're in different files
different classes wherever they can
share the same database connection
that's extremely powerful it also makes
it so that you can easily build these
things up because fixtures can depend on
other fixtures so i can have like
a string of these and the test itself
only knows the last one it needs
it can have more than one but if it just
needs i need a clean database connection
it doesn't have to care what all the
prior stuff is so it's almost like lego
bricks right you kind of build a
hierarchy and then
the test basically takes a particular
arrangement of fixtures for whatever it
needs to be and another test uses
another one and the fixture mechanism is
really what drew me to pi test it's the
magic that i was there's a whole bunch
of great reasons to use pi test but the
fixtures are what really drew me to it
because
this keeping track doing all the
bookkeeping of keeping track of the
setup and tear down for multiple levels
within your test system plus within the
x unit it's really hard to do like
something like a session scope like
where for the entire test session you've
got one thing it kind of restricts you
within unit tests to be able to do that
that's difficult whereas it's really
easy in pi test and for me
i mean a database connection might be
something that a lot of people are
familiar with
i also i do that also with testing
software that uses database but i also
test hardware stuff and a connection to
a hardware device and setting it into a
known state those are and maybe even
like setting up a waveform for me to
test with it those are all expensive
procedures that i really don't want to
do for every test they might be up into
the seconds to get set up and then i
want to run like hundreds of tests
against that without having to do those
few second setups between and that it
was like no brainer when i learned about
fixtures and how easy they are
definitely used by test now the other
thing setup and teardown are in x unit
style stuff they're like two different
functions and they used to be like
really early when i started using pi
test they were two different functions
also but they're not anymore the more
recent versions of pi test and it's been
for the last couple years at least they
have a uh actually like the last five
years but anyway there's a yield
statement so your fixture just you can
stick a yield statement right in the
middle of it anything before is your
setup anything after is your tear down
it looks weird when you first use it but
it's really convenient because i can put
this right like i can use a context
expression even and have the yield be in
the middle of that or in the middle of
really anything and you can measure you
know your tests for example yeah you can
measure it or like things that you're
keeping track of local variables within
your fixture they're still there
during the teardown so you don't have to
like store it to a global variable or
anything like that so it makes it really
convenient yeah yeah speaking of data
and setting up data one of the
interesting things i found about itest
is the whole parameterization aspect
right so you can actually
set it up so that you write one piece of
code and pass in a data structure
and then that generates a whole set of
tests that simulate different conditions
so perhaps you could kind of like go
into some of how the magic of that
happens it's pretty amazing really so
like we're talking about
parameterization and there's several
different kinds of parameterization
within pi test but let's say the normal
function parameterization is i've got a
test function
that like let's say i set up a user and
i make sure the user can log into a
system and that's great but what if the
user is different types so i've got like
maybe a an editor user type and uh like
an admin type or different roles that i
want to test i can maybe set up all the
credential junk that i need for the
different roles i can set that up into a
data structure and then pass in an array
of different roles to my test and with
the parameterization and then the test
runs once for each role and so
in a lot of other without
parameterization i would have like three
or four or i would have the number of
tests that i have number of roles
whereas with parameterization i can just
write one test and it's not like falling
off a log you do have to like work a
little bit to make sure your test is
structured such that
it can take a name thing like user role
and know what the structure is and pull
that stuff out set things up now i just
said setup you can do this all in the
test you can say okay well for a
particular role i want to like go and
log in and then i want to test whether
or not you know certain accesses work or
something like that now if that setup
code is complicated i can push that
whole thing up into a fixture
and instead of parameterizing the test i
can parameterize the fixture and then
the test doesn't know that it's being
parameterized but it still looks the
same you can run it it'll be run
multiple times
now if it really gets blowing up really
big if you've got
a parameterized test and a parameterized
fixture that maybe depends on another
fixture that's also parameterized you
can like get a huge number of test cases
really fast doing this so if you're
measured one of your measures is how
many test cases you write this is a
really great way to like blow it blow it
up and like beat the record for
everybody else
yeah it's also a sharp tool right if
you're not careful you can have a
combination really large number of tests
all taking a whole bunch of time in your
test suite just because you've made a
mistake one in one place but it's also a
great way to
there are if you've got a really cheap
test a really fast test you can say
instead of trying to pick which test
cases to run
you can just if you've got a fairly
small set you can easily set up an
exhaustive test suite that tests every
combination you know if it ends up being
like a huge number maybe it's not
beneficial but especially when you're
developing your code that might be an
interesting thing to just try now things
like hypothesis
our hypothesis is a different tool that
does like tries to guess good test cases
and stuff and input into your test and
you can use hypothesis with pi test to
try to guess good input for you know
input such that it'll break it easily so
hypothesis is pretty good that it comes
with a pre-built in plug-in for pi test
so that's pretty neat right so let's
just play in a little bit so hypothesis
is a different python library but it
kind of plugs in into pi test or is this
going to be
a part of that plug-in story that we
have with us it's kind of both
hypothesis is a different category that
you can use on its own you can also use
it with unit test but it comes pre-built
with some a pi test plug-in as part of
it so yeah but that kind of leads into
the other thing about other kind of
superpower by test especially now that
it's become so popular is the extensive
amount of plugins and extensions you can
kind of get for pi test right the other
day i was looking for something that i
was trying to test something that used
redis and i found an entire plugin that
basically just faked the entire redis
protocol for you and you could just plug
that in but it kind of made it so so
i didn't have to set up a red server
anywhere i could just do the whole thing
on my local machine
so what kind of magic does spiders do in
terms of the extensibility what is the
kind of maybe a overlying architecture
of how that architecture the plug-in
architecture works well there's some
under the hood stuff that i don't really
understand but that's okay i know it
extensively as a user would use it so
we're talking about there's like both
there's two aspects of the plug-in
system that are really cool one of them
is it makes it really easy for you as a
user to
make your own plug-in and extend it so
there's a notion of like a local plug-in
for instance we were talking about
fixtures like setting up a database and
stuff like let's say i've got that i've
got like a common database that
tons of different like microservices
that i have need to access
i can set up a little like my fixtures
for how to access it normally i can put
those really in the test file or if i'm
sharing it across multiple files pi test
has a notion of a conf test dot pi so
it's just a naming convention for a file
that's used for around the rest of the
test suite but it's kind of also a
plug-in so the conf test
file is a local plug-in
and it doesn't feel like a plug-in i
just have my fixtures in it but i can
package that as a plug-in
fairly easily and then i can use that
plug-in i can have it that plug-in to be
its own python package and i can have
different test suites in my community or
my job or something they can all use
that plug-in and use the same fixtures
so i can easily create my own create
shared code within my own team or or my
own organization so that's amazingly
helpful now there's a whole bunch of
hook functions we can use too like i can
hook into the so pi test has a hook
mechanism
that allows you to hook into different
parts of how it's running so after it
collects tests for instance i can look
at the collection before it gets run
and i can maybe modify it sort it
reorder it things like that
now i also in the reporting like there's
actually just tons of different parts of
how it's working there's hook functions
that you can hook in
and look and it's
it's not trivial a lot of these to
figure out how it's doing this and how
to use them but it's there and a lot of
people have found it useful to figure
this out so as you said there's a whole
bunch of other third-party plug-ins
that have made use of this extensibility
mechanism
and allow you to do things like i was
mentioning during test collection you
might want to reorder them well there's
a handful of like plugins that reorder
them for you they randomize them and
shift them around and randomization is a
pretty cool thing to do because if you
don't you really don't want the order
dependencies within your tests so
occasionally shuffling them around to
make sure that they don't break when you
reorder them it's a good idea
or like you said it presents these
fixture mechanisms for mocking a
database or
mocking a connection to a server so you
can like mock your requests connection
or you can record things there's plugins
to record in playback sessions and
there's all sorts of stuff you can do
with the plugin system and it's really
pretty easy to set up it's one of the
things like one of the reasons why i
said it in the pi test book that i wrote
there's a dedicated chapter on how to do
this because
when you go with a simple example it's
easy to see that it's really not that
hard to do and especially with a local
organization i think it's important for
people to be able to share code even if
they never publish on pipi it's just
shared within their organization
yeah i think that's a great point
just to kind of go into another concept
that you kind of talked about there a
little bit which is the idea of mocking
so can you tell us what is mocking and
why is it used what is its function
in testing well mostly it's to make fun
of people
well so there's a whole ecosystem around
mocking and a whole bunch of words it
kind of gets confusing when you're in
other places but within python there's a
we usually get our mocks started with
the unit test library so there's a
built-in mock mechanism that's now part
of the unit test library so even if
you're using pi test
if you're using mock if you want to mock
something we get it from the unit test
mock library but anyway the idea is it's
part of your system you want to like not
use the real thing you want to use a
fake thing and there's lots of reasons
why you might want to do that like you
said like a redis server or maybe i've
got a
access to my customer database or access
to a third-party system like stripe and
charging credit cards and stuff like
that and when i'm writing my tests i
really don't want to like hit those
things maybe i do if it's my like you
know my redis server if it's local maybe
i do want to test that but i can you
know mock that out and avoid that so
especially if i'm test if i don't i
don't really care about the logic of
that logic right now the thing i'm
focusing on maybe is the user interface
experience or something else and i don't
i want to isolate part of the system
away
so marking can be done with that and
python is like a very dynamic language
so it's fairly easy to say
after you've got a system loaded hey
this one piece in here don't use that
piece use this this new fake piece so
mocking is great at that now the other
reason to use it is
like let's say it's not that i just
don't want to
talk to my
my stripe server or something but i also
i want to make sure that the code that's
hitting the stripe system is doing it
correctly
so mocking allows us to interrogate the
calls to say okay i'm going to use this
fake stripe system
but when this bit of code runs after it
runs i want to make sure that
the stripe api calls were called
at the right time with the right content
the right data so it allows you to kind
of look into the request that you're
sending to the stripe api and making
sure that that's correct yeah super
powerful and handy yeah
so and this is just a curiosity so you
said you test hardware i'm surprised do
you not use mocks for hardware well they
would defeat the point
because i'm trying to test the hardware
but i've often heard that you know a lot
of hardware testing uses simulation
software simulation of the actual
hardware especially when it is
pre-production stuff maybe i'm usually
want to make sure that the entire
thing's working so i don't mock very
much but like for something so mocking
is often used for doing these like
hitting parts of the system that you
don't want to do i do want to say i
don't really like using mocks and i
think that there's an architecture
problem if you have to use it and i
would say that the things that we don't
want to hit during testing that should
be part of the architecture known as at
creation time did we say hey we've got a
stripe system we know we're going to
want to test this system
we don't want to hit stripe all the time
or we don't want to hit email all the
time so
designing this system this is and coming
from hardware also there's a notion of
designing for test or designing for
testability and software can do this too
to know hey there's parts of our system
that we're probably not going to want to
hit during testing so how do we verify
the rest of the system is working
correctly so one way for like maybe an
email system or something would be
designed into it a switch to say hey
turn the email system into instead of
actually sending the email just log it
to a internal
into a file or something yeah okay yeah
and then the test can re interrogate
that and check the contents to make sure
that like the sender was correct or
whatever if they want to and the same
with the stripe server or something like
that you can have like a stub one in
place but it doesn't necessarily have to
be like you know it can be during debug
only but it also could just be that's
part of your system is to switch it out
the other aspect is they maybe that's
dangerous and we really do want to have
mocks but let's make sure that like
instead of a stripe system i'm talking
to
i would have like a part of my
architecture that's the payment gateway
and it's just like one file or one
module that it's the only thing that
ever talks to stripe and then it's a
known api that i have control over so
that thing i can maybe test against a
stripe test database and make sure that
that one little tiny api
to this payment gateway
is working correctly that actually hits
something but i don't really change that
api
at all
ever and then the rest of the system can
mock instead of mocking or stubbing
stripe i can mock my payment gateway
with a fake one
and that's more safe because i know it's
never going to change now there's a
built-in part of the mocking library
that some people forget about which is
the ability to auto spec where you
instead of just saying i want a mock
thing
if you just say by default mocks like
will accept anything you pass at them
but if you auto spec them then it will
force it to only accept the api as is so
if the api ever changes then it won't
accept things that don't match the api
so that's good right so i think it's
called spec and it kind of like you can
specify the attributes and you can put
in some values for what does the api
like
software engineers you've been there
something's broken and you and your
whole team are scrambling to find and
fix it that's why you need new relic it
combines 16 different monitoring
products so you can see across your
entire software stack it pinpoints
issues down to the line of code so you
know exactly why the problem happened
and can fix it quick
get access to the whole new relic
platform and 100 gigs of data free right
now at newrelic.com
se radio
that's newrelic.com
so just to dig into the architectural
aspect that you mentioned i think that's
a great notion the idea of
designing for testing right and so if
you wanted to go about if i have a
developer who's only written like python
scripts right one-off scripts for
automating things and all that and then
suddenly i get hired into a new startup
and then they say hey nikhil we're going
to build this ecommerce website and
we're going to do it in python and i
want you to build this whole thing out
right so i'm certainly staring at this
blank canvas with a folder in it and i
need to build a project structure do you
have i mean do you have any tips or do
you have any thoughts about
how
we can go about designing a project or
even if you have an existing project how
do you actually build it in a way or
re-architected in a way that makes it
test friendly especially for pi test
testing yeah there's a lot of tips but
first off i got to say congratulations
on your interview skills for landing
this job that you're clearly not
qualified for so kudos but we can get
you there so one of the first things
like going from a normal script so when
i say script often it can really be
anything but a lot of so some of the
beginning python scripts that i wrote
there was no functions at all in there
there was no done domain or anything
there was just code that ran when you
ran it now the first thing is don't do
that so even if you take like the entire
contents of that file that you're used
to and stick it in a main method and
then have a dunder method under like
there's a thing called that we're
convinced
yeah yeah if double underscore name
equals
double underscore main in a string it's
a thing python does to tell
your script that this code is running
because somebody said python your script
name
versus importing it that little switch
makes it so that you can
both run it as a script but you can also
import it and now that it's importable i
can write a test so i can write a test
that imports my
module and then runs the main method and
hopefully
checks the output of it so code and then
maybe you know having a 7000 line file
all stuck in one main method it's
probably a bad idea so breaking your
code into different functions different
modules is a good thing because then i
can test individual pieces it's a lot
easier to test pieces than
the whole thing actually it's not but if
you've got chunk of logic is easier to
test in a small function one of the
things i get a lot of questions of of
like how do i test this thing
whether it's like you know the server or
whatever
the first questions i need to try to ask
somebody is
how do you know it's working and if you
can't answer that if you don't know what
the behavior is that's expected what the
output's supposed to be
and what like side effects happen
there's no way you can test it because
that's essentially else testing is is
checking to make sure that the behavior
is as expected and the side effects are
as expected so that's interesting so
that kind of puts me on my into so what
is your opinion about test driven
development
because i would imagine that something
which is where you have to write the
test first and then write the code that
satisfies the tests would mean that
you'd have to think about side effects
and
how to test if how to tell if
something's running up front right
yeah
yeah definitely
yeah so you're a fan of test driven
development i'm aware of test driven
development
so i am a fan of test driven development
but the thing that i call testament
development is different than what a lot
of people use
so there's really like two flavors
there's other well there's lots of
flavors but there's an original notion
of test driven development which is is
using tests to help you develop your
system over the course of time
now then there was this other thing
that is
focused on testing little tiny pieces
like and then that's like the mock
driven
test driven development which is
something that developed later and i
never got on board with that but
developing both tests and code at the
same time especially as you're
developing production code i'm
definitely a fan of that but i'm not a
stickler for the test has to be first
there's tons of times where i'm like
developing
a feature where i'm just playing with it
that i don't necessarily write the test
first i also write a lot of tests that i
throw away so i use testing for
just playing so one of the things that
people will often do when they're
developing code is like if you're
calling like you're developing a bunch
of functions within a module say
i want to call those functions to see
what they do and one of the best easiest
ways to do that is to write a test that
calls that function to see what it does
and you can even just with modern
editors you can just like select that
test file and say test and say run
without a test you'd have to write an a
specific file just to call that one
function whereas with a test you can
have like a whole slew of little helper
tests just to try things out
yeah i'm reminded of the fact that i was
getting into the business and as a
junior developer in a.net project
i had precisely this problem right i had
this thing where i was given a task to
do and i had a set of functions written
and i was like okay now how do i
actually run this and the way i did it
was basically wrote a main and then
debugged through it
on visual studio right and then
basically i got one of my seniors came
around me was like hey why don't we just
try to test and
run it in the context of the test
framework and then you don't have to
throw away the main function at the end
of the day you can actually use it as
tests and
and that was great advice i have a lot
of people start this whole like if name
equals main thing
in your module some people just stick
like calls to their code in there
and even assert methods or whatever but
it's just i mean it's not it's not
maintainable over time to keep those
running so don't be afraid especially
for exploratory stuff like that don't be
afraid to throw those away i mean or
keep them if they're helpful but
sometimes it's just it was just there
for me to learn how to how what the
problem space looks like you alluded to
i want to come back to a little bit you
alluded to the fact of if you're only
used to running small systems and you
want to create a bigger system that's
like a computer science concept of which
in like small letters of one of the big
tricks that we have as programmers is
taking a big problem
and breaking the problem into smaller
pieces
and then focusing on those pieces now
that's one of the miracles of testing is
i can have my test focused at when i've
broken things into smaller pieces i can
write the tests around those pieces to
say i think i want this piece to do this
now i'll write some tests to make sure
that it does that
and then i can forget about it and then
i can go focus my attention on the
different pieces yeah but to kind of
take the reason why i said that or
rather i brought up that particular
question was that often times i have
seen in my experience as well where
people would go about
without tests or not considering this
build huge systems that are very
connected and coupled right and i've
always found that if they had started
out with tests in like you said you know
small pieces that you write test for and
then you write another test for it
almost kind of evolves into modular code
somehow right i think that's kind of one
of the side effects of having to think
that okay when i'm writing the code
how do i actually make it so that it is
isolatable and testable that you
naturally tend towards a modular design
rather than you know building large
systems which kind of like all connected
together i've heard that claim also i
haven't seen it as an example you know
i've seen working code that is a mess
and i've seen messy code that works and
vice versa so i think hopefully if you
get used to breaking problems down
you're going to naturally modularize
things and it also has the advantage of
being able to write tests around it also
one of the benefits of the tests is that
it allows you to rewrite stuff so once
you've figured out a problem
you can look at it and go gosh this code
is a mess i mean i figured it out but
it's a mess and i can go and rewrite it
to where i'm proud of it and then my
tests verify that i didn't break
anything yeah absolutely yeah that's the
classic red green refactor cycle right
so the refactor parts comes because you
already written the tests and you have a
framework in which you can change the
structure of the code with confidence
so yeah which brings another point up so
there's obviously the ideal situation is
that you know you'll write code and your
test through an error and the error is
because your code failed or you made a
mistake or you have to correct something
but there's also the other situation
right when you have to write a new
feature or you have to change the code
for whatever business logic and your
test is now wrong right and there's
always a balance there so i've also seen
situations where people basically say
that okay you need to have a lot of code
coverage you need 100 code coverage and
i've also seen situations where
that actually leads to a thing where you
cannot change your code because as soon
as you change one place in the code a
thousand tests are broken and you have
to go and fix all of that right so is
that kind of like a sign is there kind
of like any design practices or any
design recommendations on how to design
a test suite so that it is similar it is
not going up so brittle and it doesn't
kind of break everywhere well there's a
few things about that
so yes there's ways what the primary way
is to focus on behavior testing behavior
instead of implementation so hopefully i
partly write the test so that i can
change the code so that i can rewrite
chunks to make it maybe something i'm
proud of or just because it's fun
it's sometimes fun to rewrite chunks
if the code is changing because the
behavior has changed then hopefully
tests will
fail
because they're testing for the old
behavior and so yeah we want that to
happen the other side is if instead of
testing behavior i'm really testing
implementation that's kind of where it's
also one of the dangers of mocks is
utilizing mocks a lot in your system
might cement you into one way of doing
something so be careful around that
things like a payment gateway mocking
that i know i'm going to want to mark
the payment gateway so it's okay to i
mean that's a known you made a decision
to do that but i wouldn't mock all over
the place just so that i can isolate a
function from its dependencies if the
dependencies are part of my system also
because
i want to be able to change the
implementation and do something else one
of the problems often with riddle tests
is because they're testing
implementation and not behavior
and so then if you change the
implementation your test breaks you know
we don't want that the other aspect of
it is user interface components so
testing around ui components is a design
thing and that's difficult so i
generally don't write very many tests
around a user interface i like to test
against an api instead those are often
less brittle but if you've got like
workflow stuff like if i've got like
lots of ways you could use the system
and so i've got a lot of different
workflows tested at a high level for the
whole system with the database and
everything
and thinking that those are brittle
that's like your customer that's how
your customers use it so if those tests
break when you just refactor something
your customers are going to break also
so there's a problem in your system yeah
yeah no i i hear you so it basically
like you said it depends on what kind of
tests are breaking whether it is a group
of implementation focused tests like the
ui or something like that versus
you know you're testing multiple
different ways to use your api and you
change your api and then all of them
break because well that was a
big change to a contract that you have
for all your interfaces
so that's a great point but okay let's
take it another slightly different tank
so now i have a failing test or i'm
running a large test suite and i get a
failing test right and i test basically
says okay you know there is a big red
red dot over there and it says okay it's
failing
and this is not equal to that is there a
way to kind of get more information
about what is failing can i kind of like
focus on to a particular test or a
particular way to kind of debug into it
and kind of figure out what happened so
hopefully it fails again so if you heard
the whole the joke about the software
engineer in the car so there's like
three engineers in a car they're going
down a hill and and the
brakes give out and they can't stop they
finally stop the car and they're worried
about it the hardware engineer says well
clearly it's a brake problem we should
investigate the brake system and the
electrical engineer says you know i
think the mechanism to just to indicate
that we're breaking might be broken so
we should check the electrical system
and the software engineer says before we
do anything we should push it up to the
top of the hill and see if it does it a
second time so in software we try to
reproduce the problems and so one of the
cool features that i like around pi test
is a last failed system so it's always
keeping track of what's going on of
which tests passed and failed and
especially the failures it's going to
have a list of those so that's already
built into the system to keep track of
that and we can use a flag it's lf or
last failed and there's a bunch of other
ones around that like failed first or
stuff like that but i can say just rerun
the last failed ones but one of the
benefits of that is when i rerun the
last failures
i can have more control over it so like
i can say give it a dash x for fail-off
don't run more than one like find the
first failure and just stop there and
then i can say like verbose i can have
it be more verbose and i can say things
and that just gives me a lot like more
trace back it fills up the trace back
more i also can have control over the
traceback i can say i want a short trace
back or a long one
or the full one
and then the one i really love also is
to show locals so when it tests to have
for during the traceback also print out
all the local variables and what their
contents are it's really handy to be
able to rerun that again and then for
big sweets there's a stepwise that came
in a couple versions ago that i really
love using to where i can say
instead of just doing the last failed i
can step through a suite so i'm going to
run the suite until it hits a failure
then it stops and then i can maybe
change some code or change the test or
add some more debugging
and then i run it again with the same
stepwise and instead of starting at the
top
it starts at that last failure and just
reruns that if that passes well if it
fails it just stops again but if it
passes it continues to the next failure
so it just keeps on stepping through to
all the next failures it's really handy
very cool yeah very cool that's actually
something i did not know
i'm going to try it out next so
obviously pi test is a tool that we can
run on the cli and it's a standard
scripting tool is there any special
considerations that we need to think
about when we're going to try and put it
into maybe our ci cd pipeline
does it have any dependencies that need
to be varied out or can we just use it
as a part of the python requirements
file and you're done i usually separate
them out to have not as the requirements
for the system but
have test requirements so either a
separate requirements file so some
people do that of like two different for
an application if you're using
requirements you'd have a separate
requirements it's usually called dev
though because we want our developers to
have it also but ci system can load that
or there is like if it's a package
project you can have uh extra
dependencies so i can say like you know
pip installed foo with brackets in it
test or something and then it brings in
the test requirements so those are ways
you can do that but then other people
just
have that as part of their ci pipeline
to say hey it's going to have to bring
in pi tests so pull that in right
is there kind of like i remember you
mentioned in your book there is this
tool called talks that you can use for
testing various versions of python and
managing
environments and stuff how does that
kind of fit in into the whole pie test
story fantastic story i like to use them
together but there's i mean there's
other versions you can do but so in c
like continuous integration you've got
the server running your tests but you
can do something similar locally with
talks nox is another option as well but
i particularly like talks and
traditionally it's around testing
multiple versions of python so if i've
got like let's say i'm developing a
library i want to test it against
several versions of python i have to
have those versions loaded on my
computer for this to work
but if i run i can set up talks such
that it will
create virtual environments
with multiple versions of python
and then build my not not just load my
software but build it
in those versions load and then run them
and test everything out run my tests
within that environment i can also make
it just do built once and then test
against that and actually i probably
misspoke i think it just doesn't build
once but it's like a ci pipeline on your
desktop so you can test a whole bunch of
stuff out so that's really handy to be
able to test out you don't have to do it
against multiple versions of python
though it could be something else like
let's say
i am writing a django plugin and i want
to test it against multiple versions of
django i can set up talks to do that to
test on multiple versions and then yeah
within pi test it's kind of fun
i didn't learn this until i was
developing writing the second version of
the book is there's a cool way that you
can use talks and pie tests together
to debug just a single
talks environment so like let's say pi
tests you know python
310 is breaking for your package
you can rerun and set up all those extra
flags like the show locals and all that
stuff you can pass those in and just
set it to one environment which is
pretty handy or you can use pdb and step
through it just right there so
right great so i think we're kind of
like reaching towards the end of our
discussion here
is there anything that we missed that
you would particularly like to talk
about in terms of our discussion yeah
one of the things i really want to we we
brought up test driven development once
or for a little while
one of the things in a lot of the tdd
discussions talk about is
testing your code is worth it i believe
that they also say when you start doing
it developing with tests is slower
but it's worth it because you'll have
less maintenance in the future and i
just don't buy it if i think developing
with test is faster than developing
without tests i don't think it's slower
that's an interesting hypothesis is that
based on your experience or is that i
mean why do you say that it is faster
because i'm doing it anyway so i'm like
let's say like you said if i'm writing
like a main function to call my
functions writing tests to call my
functions is easier and it's not that
big of a leap to go okay what tests did
i write just to develop the thing
i probably can spend like 45 minutes and
clean these up and they'd be a decent
test suite for my system and to begin
with and then i've got checking it in so
i'm using helping tests to
run my code while i'm developing it i'm
using tests to help make sure it doesn't
break in the future it doesn't i don't
think it takes long for you to learn
testing and be comfortable with it
enough to where you're actually
developing faster than you would without
tests yeah i mean i tend to agree even
especially with the framework like pi
test which is so flexible and like you
said it so it's so easy to do it that
you almost feel tempted that you know
like wow i mean it's such a beautiful
way to do it and you don't you feel like
you know you wanted to write some tests
so yeah that's a great point so just in
terms of completeness so how can our
audience follow connect with you i
believe you are already a podcast host
and you have a couple of podcasts and we
will add links to those podcasts here
but maybe you want to talk a little bit
about other ways
maybe a little bit about the podcast as
well sure this prep the primary way i
hang out on twitter a lot so
i'm at brian hawkin on twitter and then
i've got test and code which i have to
enunciate because some people think i'm
saying testing code it's
testandcode.com and then also the
pythonbytes podcast which is at
pythonbytes.fm those are the two
podcasts yeah and twitter one of the fun
things about the test end code community
is we have a slack channel too so
there's a slack channel you can sign up
for and
there's like hundreds of people hanging
out answering asking and answering
questions around testing especially
around pi tests but they'll around other
python topics too like if you've got
some weird database that you're
connecting to and you don't know how to
test it there's probably somebody in
there that's using it also that's pretty
great and i've started blogging again i
started this whole thing by blogging and
i'm doing it again it's at
pythontest.com
awesome
thank you so much ryan it was a great
discussion
i'm sure our audience would be looking
forward to reading more about it on your
book which is python testing with pi
test
and it's from the pragmatic programmers
press which is again one of my favorite
publishers as well so thank you again
brian oh thank you again i want to add
one more note the second edition also
was written such that it feels like a
course
and that's on purpose because i do want
to turn it into a video course so that's
one of the things i'll be working on
this year is turning it into a video
course awesome okay good luck with that
i'm looking forward to it thanks and
thanks for having me on the show this
was fun okay
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening